<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Essays on shyer</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Essays on shyer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 09:15:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://wickedb.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Future of Hardware Security</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/third-post/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 09:15:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/third-post/</guid><description>Hardware Security Challenges As our devices become more integrated into our lives, hardware security becomes increasingly important. This post explores emerging trends in this field.
Critical Vulnerabilities Some areas of concern in modern hardware:
Side-channel attacks on cryptographic implementations Supply chain vulnerabilities in chip manufacturing Secure boot and trusted execution environments Promising Solutions The industry is developing innovative approaches to these challenges, including physically unclonable functions (PUFs) and formal verification methods.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="hardware-security-challenges">Hardware Security Challenges</h2>
<p>As our devices become more integrated into our lives, hardware security becomes increasingly important. This post explores emerging trends in this field.</p>
<h3 id="critical-vulnerabilities">Critical Vulnerabilities</h3>
<p>Some areas of concern in modern hardware:</p>
<ul>
<li>Side-channel attacks on cryptographic implementations</li>
<li>Supply chain vulnerabilities in chip manufacturing</li>
<li>Secure boot and trusted execution environments</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="promising-solutions">Promising Solutions</h3>
<p>The industry is developing innovative approaches to these challenges, including physically unclonable functions (PUFs) and formal verification methods.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll be sharing more insights from my research in this area soon!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>My Journey with FPGA Development</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/second-post/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 08:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/second-post/</guid><description>Exploring FPGA Development In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experiences working with FPGAs and the challenges I&amp;rsquo;ve overcome in hardware design projects.
Key Learnings Some important lessons from my FPGA journey:
Understanding timing constraints is crucial Simulation before synthesis saves debugging time Hardware debugging requires different approaches than software Future Directions I&amp;rsquo;m excited to explore more complex designs and possibly contribute to open-source FPGA projects in the future.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="exploring-fpga-development">Exploring FPGA Development</h2>
<p>In this post, I&rsquo;ll share my experiences working with FPGAs and the challenges I&rsquo;ve overcome in hardware design projects.</p>
<h3 id="key-learnings">Key Learnings</h3>
<p>Some important lessons from my FPGA journey:</p>
<ul>
<li>Understanding timing constraints is crucial</li>
<li>Simulation before synthesis saves debugging time</li>
<li>Hardware debugging requires different approaches than software</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m excited to explore more complex designs and possibly contribute to open-source FPGA projects in the future.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more technical posts!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Portfolio Project: Example Work</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/portfolio-project/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 22:55:30 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/portfolio-project/</guid><description>helo Portfolio Project Example This is an example of how you can showcase your portfolio projects on your website. Each project post can include details about your work, process, and outcomes.
Project Overview Client/Project Name: Example Project
Timeline: January - March 2025
Role: Your role in the project
Tools Used: List of tools and technologies
The Challenge Describe the problem or challenge that this project addressed. What were the goals and requirements?</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="helo">helo</h1>
<h2 id="portfolio-project-example">Portfolio Project Example</h2>
<p>This is an example of how you can showcase your portfolio projects on your website. Each project post can include details about your work, process, and outcomes.</p>
<h3 id="project-overview">Project Overview</h3>
<p><strong>Client/Project Name</strong>: Example Project<br>
<strong>Timeline</strong>: January - March 2025<br>
<strong>Role</strong>: Your role in the project<br>
<strong>Tools Used</strong>: List of tools and technologies</p>
<h3 id="the-challenge">The Challenge</h3>
<p>Describe the problem or challenge that this project addressed. What were the goals and requirements?</p>
<h3 id="the-process">The Process</h3>
<p>Explain your approach and methodology. What steps did you take to complete the project?</p>
<ol>
<li>Research and Discovery</li>
<li>Planning and Strategy</li>
<li>Design and Development</li>
<li>Testing and Refinement</li>
<li>Delivery and Implementation</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="the-result">The Result</h3>
<p>Share the outcomes and impact of your work. What was achieved? Include metrics or testimonials if available.</p>
<h3 id="reflections">Reflections</h3>
<p>What did you learn from this project? What would you do differently next time?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>My First Post</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 22:46:55 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</guid><description>Welcome to My Website This is my first post on my new personal website. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share my thoughts, projects, and experiences here.
What to Expect On this website, you&amp;rsquo;ll find:
Personal essays and reflections Project showcases and portfolio work Thoughts on various topics that interest me About the Site This site is built with Hugo using the PaperModX theme. It&amp;rsquo;s designed to be clean, fast, and focused on content.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="welcome-to-my-website">Welcome to My Website</h2>
<p>This is my first post on my new personal website. I&rsquo;m excited to share my thoughts, projects, and experiences here.</p>
<h3 id="what-to-expect">What to Expect</h3>
<p>On this website, you&rsquo;ll find:</p>
<ul>
<li>Personal essays and reflections</li>
<li>Project showcases and portfolio work</li>
<li>Thoughts on various topics that interest me</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="about-the-site">About the Site</h3>
<p>This site is built with <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a> using the <a href="https://github.com/reorx/hugo-PaperModX">PaperModX</a> theme. It&rsquo;s designed to be clean, fast, and focused on content.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more posts coming soon!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>