<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Essays on shyer</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Essays on shyer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 08:30:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://wickedb.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Some cool weblinks</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/coolsite/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 08:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/coolsite/</guid><description>I force my fav weblinks upon you Cameron&amp;rsquo;s world - A collage of old internet sites Rauno&amp;rsquo;s UI portfolio - Especially love the flow project Archive any link - pls also donate to the internet archive Obviously xkcd Bret victor&amp;rsquo;s ladder of abstraction Andy matuschak&amp;rsquo;s work Through the looking glass, lewis carroll Youtube links (that exist for now) 2 idiots 1 keyboard I dont care inator Louvre lover A place that language cannot reach Probably the best video on complex adaptive systems A summary of The Historia Naturalis Abridged (Books I-II)</description><content:encoded>&lt;h1 id="i-force-my-fav-weblinks-upon-you">I force my fav weblinks upon you&lt;/h1>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.cameronsworld.net/">Cameron&amp;rsquo;s world&lt;/a> - A collage of old internet sites&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://rauno.me/projects">Rauno&amp;rsquo;s UI portfolio&lt;/a> - Especially love the flow project&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://archive.ph/">Archive any link&lt;/a> - pls also &lt;a href="https://archive.org/donate/">donate&lt;/a> to the internet archive&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/538/">Obviously xkcd&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://worrydream.com/LadderOfAbstraction/">Bret victor&amp;rsquo;s ladder of abstraction&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://andymatuschak.org/">Andy matuschak&amp;rsquo;s work&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/12">Through the looking glass, lewis carroll&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="youtube-links-that-exist-for-now">Youtube links (that exist for now)&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u8qgehH3kEQ">2 idiots 1 keyboard&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z0ZkH7dnd-4">I dont care inator&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FObgAnzvtaU">Louvre lover&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Oo4SdrE2L_U">A place that language cannot reach&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8QaP43sFO5A">Probably the best video on complex adaptive systems&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A summary of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5L5tjscy85U">The Historia Naturalis Abridged (Books I-II)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol></content:encoded><category>Essays</category><category>exploratory</category><media:content url="https://wickedb.github.io/images/weblinks.png" medium="image"/></item><item><title>Formal systems as simulators</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/formal-systems/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 08:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/formal-systems/</guid><description>Thinking of formal systems as simulators A formal system is a set of symbols and rules that we use to derive theorems. For example, the imaginary number system is a well-known formal system, with one of its most prominent symbols being ‘i’. Another well-known example is the symbol F commonly used to represent force in Newtonian mechanics.
We often rely on the abstractions formal systems offer as frameworks for reasoning. Any formal system consists of a rule-book with symbols, axioms, and theorems derived from the axioms.</description><content:encoded>&lt;h1 id="thinking-of-formal-systems-as-simulators">Thinking of formal systems as simulators&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>A formal system is a set of symbols and rules that we use to derive theorems. For example, the imaginary number system is a well-known formal system, with one of its most prominent symbols being ‘i’. Another well-known example is the symbol F commonly used to represent force in Newtonian mechanics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We often rely on the abstractions formal systems offer as frameworks for reasoning. Any formal system consists of a rule-book with symbols, axioms, and theorems derived from the axioms. Rather than treating these systems like static-rule books for abstraction, I propose that it is useful to take a step back and think of a formal system as a simulator, a tool we use to simulate environments, in order to conceptualize what it means for us to need to shift from one formal system to another.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let us consider a situation where we want to find the force exerted on a cement block by a trolley. One way is to use CAD software that can simulate Newtonian mechanics to compute the resultant force. Another way would be to take the help of an abstraction, like a free body diagram (FBD) with arrows on it. In this case I’m simulating a real-world concept—say, an object being pushed. The FBD, with my interpretation of its arrows and numbers, helps determine the resultant force. If a formal system is a symbol manipulator that helps represent and model a complex concept, then it can act like a simulator for some concept you have in mind. A characteristic of both these simulators is that they help externalize concepts as a concrete set of symbols and rules – a block of wood being pushed versus a FBD of the block or a computer-simulated model.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This implies that we cannot blame a formal system for being inexpressive when it was set up to simulate something else. If I have a new concept I want to express, I need to find a formal system that has the ability to represent the ideas or phenomena I want it to. I will need to survey all available formal systems, assign meanings to the symbols and axioms, and see if the implications of the derived theorems really do express my concept. But since this sounds exhausting, we tend to create a formal system from scratch with the concept we want to express at the back of our minds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If I built a simulator to use certain symbols that meet some criteria (axioms), the only way for the simulation to fail to express a concept is if the criteria themselves are incapable of expressing it. Similarly, the formal system was created to express my concept, but that is only my expectation. A formal system doesn’t come with meanings pre-installed. Its symbols and rules are neutral until interpreted. And its expressiveness is constrained by its interpretation. So when it no longer can express a concept, it means our expectations have shifted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is what it means when we say Newtonian mechanics ‘breaks’: it no longer simulates, with its symbols and theorems, the world we want to express. The expressiveness is not a formal system&amp;rsquo;s inherent property, and instead depends on how it was interpreted. Thus, the shift to a new formal system, for example quantum mechanics with its bra-ket notations, can be seen as outgrowing an older system because our expectations have evolved. Like any simulator, a formal system can only express what it was initially expected to, until it no longer can.&lt;/p></content:encoded><category>Essays</category><category>inquisitive</category><media:content url="https://wickedb.github.io/images/threeboys.jpg" medium="image"/></item><item><title>The academic who sold his ferrari</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/ferrari/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 08:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/ferrari/</guid><description>The academic who sold his ferrari It is commonly understood that an individual&amp;rsquo;s relationship with money has a significant impact on their approach to financial matters. A complex or difficult relationship with money may arise from experiences such as witnessing poverty, experiencing arguments over money during childhood, or being interested in science. The consequences of these early scars can manifest in adulthood as gambling, overspending, or entering academia.
The psychology behind an academic&amp;rsquo;s relationship with money needs to be studied carefully but not academically.</description><content:encoded>&lt;h1 id="the-academic-who-sold-his-ferrari">The academic who sold his ferrari&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>It is commonly understood that an individual&amp;rsquo;s relationship with money has a significant impact on their approach to financial matters. A complex or difficult relationship with money may arise from experiences such as witnessing poverty, experiencing arguments over money during childhood, or being interested in science. The consequences of these early scars can manifest in adulthood as gambling, overspending, or entering academia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The psychology behind an academic&amp;rsquo;s relationship with money needs to be studied carefully but not academically. Many assume the first rule of academia is to &amp;lsquo;publish or perish&amp;rsquo;, but they are mistaken. The real first rule of academia is to disregard money entirely, even when fully funded. Any research student that wants to make money needs to be taught this lesson.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These days academics can signal their membership to academia in many ways. The most common signal is quoting Feynman, which is known to invoke godlike genius in the quoter. But in pre-Feynman days, what was the signal academics used? Feynman himself signalled his membership to academia by detailing how he turned down a higher paying job offer. This tradition is well-respected and has stood the test of time. Turning down high paying jobs is a mark of a distinguished academic but this must be done publicly. This must also be mentioned to any junior academic seeking employment as proof that they can &amp;ldquo;get a job anytime&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These signals are often used to smoke out outsiders. For example, when Naval Ravikant said, &amp;ldquo;One Einstein is worth a legion of PhD drones,&amp;rdquo; it was clear that he&amp;rsquo;d never pursued a PhD himself. Anyone with a PhD knows that Einstein has a terrible h-index. The h-index is a trusted metric that measures academic impact. Another example is when Paul Graham said, &amp;ldquo;If it didn’t suck, they wouldn’t have had to make it prestigious.&amp;rdquo; There was no need for him to be so harsh on academia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While the disregard for money in academia may have originated as a signal between academics, it may also have Freudian roots. It is well known that academics often have a great relationship with their parents (who may also be academics). The lesser known reason for this rapport is the aforementioned disregard for money. Nothing brings you closer to your parents than needing them to pay your bills. Some might argue, in a true Freudian spirit, that academics love their parents too much to split up the family or the bill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Interestingly the most complicated money relationship is not between a PI and their own salary, but actually between the PI and their mentee&amp;rsquo;s salary. The PI must ensure the mentee is paid but not paid enough. The scientific hunger (publish or perish) must be kept alive. Other techniques that can be used to keep this hunger alive are requesting thesis updates in quick succession or suggesting that progress is too slow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The importance of keeping scientific hunger (publish or perish) alive comes to light when writing an academic paper. In any academic publication, the author names are ordered in decreasing order of time spent working and increasing order of pay. To put it simply, we start with the first author and work our way up to the PI. This smooth team-work is disrupted when there are industry collaborators involved. Because industry collaborators don&amp;rsquo;t have scientific hunger (they&amp;rsquo;re too well-paid) they often ask annoying questions like &amp;ldquo;Why don&amp;rsquo;t we run more tests?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Why aren&amp;rsquo;t the results better?&amp;rdquo;. If the mentee did not have enough scientific hunger (publish or perish), the publication would be stalled to get better results with better methods. Thus, we would have no research published if the scientific hunger (publish or perish) of a junior researcher is vanquished.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A wide-spread misconception is that scientific exploration requires wealth and resources. This is entirely untrue. I was going to provide supporting arguments but my PI just asked for more thesis updates so I will leave the rest as ‘future work’.&lt;/p></content:encoded><category>Essays</category><category>hyperlogical</category><media:content url="https://wickedb.github.io/images/threeboys.jpg" medium="image"/></item><item><title>In praise of Doofenshmirtz</title><link>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/doof/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 16:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://wickedb.github.io/posts/doof/</guid><description>The cultural significance of Heinz Doofenshmirtz Abstract Dr. Heinz Doofenshmirtz is a recurring character in Phineas and Ferb. He is a scientist whose inventions usually interfere with the main plot by the end of an episode.
This paper analyzes Doofenshmirtz as a social figure in the 21st century. It reflects on his familial bonds, the socio-economic ramifications of his inventions, his political ideologies, and the intersection of science and humanity.</description><content:encoded>&lt;h1 id="the-cultural-significance-of-heinz-doofenshmirtz">The cultural significance of Heinz Doofenshmirtz&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Dr. Heinz Doofenshmirtz is a recurring character in Phineas and Ferb. He is a scientist whose inventions usually interfere with the main plot by the end of an episode.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This paper analyzes Doofenshmirtz as a social figure in the 21st century. It reflects on his familial bonds, the socio-economic ramifications of his inventions, his political ideologies, and the intersection of science and humanity.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-childhood-of-a-tortured-genius">The Childhood of a Tortured Genius&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Doofenshmirtz grew up in Drusselstein, his parents are abusive, and he has a younger brother named Roger. This family dynamic is what drives him, forms his moral backbone, and gives him a unique worldview.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He recollects that his brother became his family&amp;rsquo;s favorite very early on. But Doofenshmirtz demonstrates incredible growth and poise when facing his rocky past. He calmly recites his backstory to Perry the Platypus without emotional agitation. He also is a caring father and throws a birthday party every year for his daughter Vanessa. He chooses not to perpetuate the cycle of abuse and is on good terms with his ex-wife, who divorced him over a sock puppet. The sock puppet symbolizes the widespread phenomenon of the hive-mind, lack of individuality, and the illusion of free will.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="platyplus---an-advanced-nemesis">Platyplus - An Advanced Nemesis&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Perry the Platypus is a secret agent at OWCA and Dr. Doofenshmirtz&amp;rsquo;s nemesis. Though Doofenshmirtz is thoroughly skilled at spotting Perry, he never assumes any platypus is Perry. His unwillingness to stereotype platypuses is indicative of his subtle yet eye-opening commentary about racial, gender, species, and economic stereotypes. He always briefs Perry on his plan and motivation, sometimes involving his backstories. He slowly builds Perry&amp;rsquo;s confidence and trust and gives Perry a chance to support his cause. Each time, Doofenshmirtz skillfully displays interpersonal skills such as giving someone a second chance and setting boundaries by cursing them as they leave.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perry initially plays it cool and doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to reciprocate his enemy — or nemesii — feelings. But eventually, when Perry catches Doofenshmirtz cheating with Peter The Panda, he is visibly hurt. He also helps set up Vanessa&amp;rsquo;s birthday party. Doofenshmirtz thus finds himself a nemesis who reciprocates his feelings through slow trust-building techniques like over-sharing.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-morally-grey-evil-scientist">The Morally Grey Evil Scientist&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Doofenshmirtz&amp;rsquo;s ambition is to take over the Tri-state Area. Before becoming an Evil Scientist, he was in the Bratwurst business (Doofenshmirtz Quality Bratwurst). He showed loyalty to his German heritage but was disappointed by American social, economic, and cultural trends that put him out of business (Hot-dogs), which might have triggered him into being an Evil Scientist. He honed his skills in silence till he could create the deadly &lt;em>Hot-Dog-Vendor-Revenge-Inator&lt;/em>. His unique insight into the challenges of bringing cultural roots to a foreign country must be capitalized on and heeded by any government deciding on immigration laws. To quote him, &amp;ldquo;I was headed to a Golden Land of Opportunity, a land with a pioneering spirit which welcomed misfits like me, but I ended up in America&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="inventions-science-and-human-progress">Inventions, Science, and Human Progress&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Doofenshmirtz’s inventions show unparalleled engineering skills and are custom-made for each situation (though he sometimes uses blueprints from the internet). His inventions break down or explode after one use to prevent misuse and patent violations. Applications for this single-use technique are a precedent for weapon regulations and a warning to world governments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another aspect of his engineering prowess is his ability to make a new device every episode within his monthly alimony check. It takes extreme craftsmanship and efficiency in design to achieve this. NASA vigorously studies his Space Launches and still struggles to launch space vessels at the Doof Budget Limit.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-academic-epidemic">The Academic Epidemic&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Doofenshmirtz has a doctorate that he bought online, a deep inquiry into the current state of academia itself. What is a real doctorate? Is paying for a Ph.D. program the same as purchasing a doctorate online? The latter option is cheaper — both in terms of money and time. His decision to purchase his doctorate can also be a direct attempt to assert dominance over his demanding guide (As referenced in the song &lt;em>I Must Impress My Professor&lt;/em>). The show also sheds light on darker elements of academia in the song &lt;em>Evil For Extra Credit&lt;/em>, where an unpaid intern goes to the extent of being Evil for college credits.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="politics-as-art---performative-and-intentional-satire">Politics as art - Performative and Intentional Satire&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>His political opinions reflect his values and morals and guide him through his life. As the founder of LOVEMUFFIN, he understands the intricate details of organizing a party and the secrets of politics. His expressions of political and cultural opinions are in clever metaphors or satire. In the song &lt;em>There’s a Platypus Controlling Me&lt;/em>, Doofenshmirtz manages to ignite and open the minds of teenagers to propaganda and corporate greed without explicitly stating these topics. He also raises public awareness of reality TV scams and extortion in the interrupted television advertisement for the &lt;em>Telethon of Evil&lt;/em> called &lt;em>Give Me Your Money&lt;/em>. His education methods are simple and accessible — Mr. Fletcher immediately declares Give Me Your Money as clever satire.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In conclusion, Doofenshmirtz is a revolutionary and visionary figure who serves as a role model to any child watching him. His insights and opinions make one think rather than blindly accept and change our relationship with devices and technology. His inventions are a brilliant display of what hard work and having a nemesis can make one achieve.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[1] D. Povenmire and J. Marsh, &lt;em>Phineas and Ferb&lt;/em>. Burbank, CA, USA: Disney Television Animation, 2007–2015.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] D. Povenmire and J. Marsh, “I Must Impress My Professor,” &lt;em>Phineas and Ferb&lt;/em>, season 3, episode 32, aired Aug. 24, 2012. Burbank, CA, USA: Disney Television Animation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[3] D. Povenmire and J. Marsh, “Evil for Extra Credit,” &lt;em>Phineas and Ferb&lt;/em>, season 3, episode 40, aired Sep. 28, 2012. Burbank, CA, USA: Disney Television Animation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[4] D. Povenmire and J. Marsh, “There’s a Platypus Controlling Me,” &lt;em>Phineas and Ferb&lt;/em>, season 2, episode 32, aired Oct. 2, 2009. Burbank, CA, USA: Disney Television Animation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[5] D. Povenmire and J. Marsh, “Give Me Your Money,” &lt;em>Phineas and Ferb&lt;/em>, season 2, episode 52, aired Jul. 30, 2010. Burbank, CA, USA: Disney Television Animation.&lt;/p></content:encoded><category>Essays</category><category>hyperlogical</category><media:content url="https://wickedb.github.io/images/doof.avif" medium="image"/></item></channel></rss>